A software engineer needs to write code.
If you're not writing code, you're not a
software engineer.
>> This is Yo-kim [music] Rect. He grew to
be one of the few distinguished
engineers among thousands at Uber. And I
asked him about how he did it. What are
the typical ways to have your work being
influencing [music] more and more
engineers?
>> I like the idea of like you become a
forceful multiplier by allowing other
people to work better and faster.
[music]
>> He was also on a ton of promo
committees. So I asked him about what
most engineers never get to see. What
does it mean when you're saying promos
are not fair? Sometimes
>> it gets super unfair because it all
depends on how good is your manager at
presenting your case. And if you have a
[__] manager, you have a [__] case.
>> Is there an engineering mistake that you
saw happen at Uber that was only obvious
in hindsight?
>> And I maybe somebody's going to be super
angry about this. I don't know. But uh
>> here's the full episode.
What was the initial problem that you
were solving and the story behind the
project that eventually got you promoted
to distinguished?
>> Not that long after I started at Uber,
we were at the local office in Denmark,
we had been tasked with building a new
data store for Uber. like previously ran
on just Postgress single instance like
just a big ass machine and lot of like a
lot of replicas and stuff like that but
like a single database and that was kind
projected to run out at a certain point
in time so before that point in time we
had to like have a new data store in
place uh so in the office we were
building a new have object store that's
called schemalist there's also a lot of
stuff about that out there u schema is
bas based on shed my sql my job was
primar primarily handling all those my
SQL shots, managing and operating them,
monitoring, scaling, all that stuff. And
in the early setup, it was basically
just like bare metal puppets and my SQL.
And so every time you had to like do a
promote a a master promotion or any kind
of maintenance or replacement, you had
to do some puppet mangling. You had
login mangled puppet, hope for the best.
And that was kind of it was pretty hard
and it got harder and harder because the
system kind of scaled more and more uh
or grew more and more and so at around
that time also like it's not that dugger
was super new at that point in time but
containerization was fairly fairly new
concept still uh some people were using
it some people weren't kubernetus I
think was out in like it just got
released in the like the first alpha
version um just around that time so I
had the like I at some point we kind
start talking about I like why don't we
actually just run the databases in DA so
that we can both run different MySQL
versions more easily we don't have to
like have the entire host we can
actually run multiple databases on a
single host because when you run the
sharded my SQL things it's a bit
expensive if you want your own database
and that then requires probably at least
nine physical servers to run a database
that it gets pretty expensive especially
because you're not going to utilize it
So why don't we why don't we virtualize
and containerize some of that so that we
can improve so we can improve
utilization but also it becomes much
more easy to manage if we then also get
take that idea that's become very common
now but was very uncommon back then
which is let's define what we want to
have like a goal state or an intent uh
and then have a system that can kind of
take you there so you don't have this
procedural
uh promote us promote a new master or
replace something you just say we want
cluster it needs to have nine uh we want
a database we have nine nine individual
clusters three nodes each and then make
that work and don't care about the
details. So that was basically the idea
uh like roughly we built that for
schemas first and that worked out pretty
well. Uh there was like a whole
ecosystem around that was also
monitoring and management and version
control. It was like it was like all
back then a was not githubs. Uh I have
like a somewhat of a version to GitHubs
because GitHub is like a oneway thing.
Uh you push something, you hope for the
best. There's not really any there's no
feedback involved. Uh so you don't
really know if stuff is going to work or
not uh or how far it is and there's no
orchestration. So we built a whole
orchestration layer and monitoring on
top of like a traditional GitHubs uh
GitHubs uh strategy and that kind of
took off and it made us
much better at scaling and much better
at monitoring and much better at
operating and so over time we were like
okay so we did that for that part uh and
then the next idea was basically why
don't we why don't we do that for all
the different databases that we run and
was basically that what became the Odin
effort
uh which was basically just can we build
something similar that can
run work for any kind of stakehold
so that ideally we have a single team
that can operate an entire fleet doing
host maintenance doing database
management doing scaling all that stuff
which was previously every single back
then every database technology had its
own team attached to it and they did
bare metal they did host management the
host monitoring provisioning,
decommissioning, database management,
all that stuff. And it was just a lot of
like everybody had their own tool chain.
It was super wasteful. So basically the
idea was can can we actually can we can
we make a single platform that can
handle all that uh and that that
basically then became yeah Odin uh and
that took a while let [laughter] me say
that uh for many reasons like there's
there's organizational like or like
there's just people because they already
built many many teams built their own
tool chain like why do we why do we use
something else but from a local point of
view it's like doesn't make any sense.
Um, so it just took a while a while is
like yes and yes to convince everybody
that was actually a good idea and then
actually get it rolled out and also
getting it to work with like
technologies that are not that were in
that are inherently
not like cloud ready or like contain
container ready like HDFS for example or
or Kafka used to also be notoriously bad
at like moving stuff around dynamically.
It's like just not a thing. Uh because
like host names are encoded everywhere
and pod numbers and like you need to
shuffle data and there's no good way of
shuffling data really. So getting all
that to work uh it just took a lot of
time uh and effort. Uh but basically the
scope but basically the that that
project just grew and grew and grew in
scope from like a very like uh single
thing where we just need we need just
need to manage our own team stuff to
actually managing the entire company on
the stateful side and when I when I left
it was actually running all the like all
the stateful workloads at uh which is
like [sighs]
I don't remember the exact numbers by
now but like when I left I think we had
like around 120,000 physical servers
under our control. H and like around
half a million like databases. Uh so
like all collocated and whatever and
running on
being being kind of operated by a team
of 20ish people which to me is like
pretty insane. There was still like
database teams that did the actual
database like Cassandra, MySQL like
expertise, but just the fleet management
part of it um like the ability to be
able to upgrade a kernel with a single
click uh or rotate like decommission
data centers or commission new data all
that stuff which usually takes a whole
lot of manual effort.
That's that kind of over time got got
pretty advanced. In my understanding the
initial motivation was two main things.
One is the the fragmentation of the
machines. So not everyone needed a full
instance. So you could save a lot of
capacity. And then the other one it
sounds like maybe even the bigger one is
the dev velocity or the engineering time
savings cuz you don't need as many
production engineers to manage all these
instances. And also just the consistency
of of that part like you want the kind
of the same availability all over the
place. You don't want to have everybody
invent
ways of making sure that servers are
working and when do you discover
something is broken? Uh when how do you
discover that a disc doesn't work any
long or whatever it might be. Like you
don't want everybody to go around do
that doing that by themselves. You kind
of want that to just be done once.
Sounds like you didn't have a grand plan
for it to eventually be all of managing
all of Uber's uh stateful workloads. So
what is it that you saw at the beginning
and how did you convince people that you
should start using um Docker for
databases?
>> Well, so one of the good things about
Uber especially in the early days was
just a lot of freedom. That freedom also
came with a lot of cost. I think at some
point somebody counted that we were
using Adubo there were like something
like 52 maybe different database
technologies in use in the company which
is like that's a lot. Uh uh but on the
other hand we also had the freedom to
basically pick what we wanted. Um so the
decision was was a fairly easy one
because we didn't have to like there
were not a lot of people who had to be
involved in it. there was some people
but it was not a lot of people who had
to be involved in it. Um so in that
sense it was fairly it was fairly easy
on the on like the first thing because
we just did it for our team by ourselves
and that was like how Uber operated for
better for worse. Um
so that part was pretty easy. I think
the the harder part was when we kind of
realized we should really be doing this
for everything. uh there it became a a
bigger project to kind of convince
people that it's the right thing and and
and we also did not con try to convince
everybody at the same time. We said
we're going to build this thing. The
long-term idea is to make to do it for
everything, but we're going to start
like it would be a very incremental
effort going to start with with the
stuff that we own in our office. Then
we're going to do the things that are
owned by
our our friends uh in other departments
and then we're go going to broader and
broader to people who who are more more
resistant to to stuff like this. Uh that
we kind of that we knew up front. Uh we
also knew that we like we're not going
to have like a ready platform like from
day one anyway. So we don't want to have
everybody on on day one. Um, but baby
was like a like I always have like a I
don't want to force anything down
anybody's throat. Uh, so I just want
like I want to build I prefer to build
something and ensure that it actually
works and then people can kind of say
okay that maybe isn't that bad than if
they actually see it work somewhere. So
a more incremental approach to to the
whole thing. And I think that that
helped a lot. It also took a very long
time.
>> When you said there were challenges when
you were influencing the other teams uh
to adopt this, what was the main push
back that you'd hear and how did you
convince people?
>> Well, I think one push back is just that
we already have something and it works.
So, it's a waste to do something else.
Um I and I I can see where I see that
argument, but it's also a kind of local
perspective. It's not a global
perspective. Like when we built this, it
was more of like from like a companywide
perspective of like we want to improve
the general state of stateful workloads.
We don't just want to improve your
thing. Uh so it does also come with a
little bit of like yeah so some things
will be much nicer but some things will
also be
kind of annoying.
uh like for example uh because Uber
didn't and still doesn't have a full uh
uh software defined network where you
can just like
virtually move IP addresses around and
host names. You like if you get a new
host you get a new host name you get a
random port number and that's it. So you
can you can't like do a logical move of
something and that that just for some
storage technologies it makes it really
really hard. Um, and that's of course
pretty annoying. Uh, so you so that that
that from like a local team perspective
can be like quite frustrating if you
then have to like you have tooling that
kind of works and now you have to
rebuild it in in a very different
paradigm and it seems like a bit waste
of time but it really isn't because you
get that you get that large scale
benefit uh because you also you get a
lot of stuff for free. Like for example,
at some point we were like, okay, we
built the basic platform.
Now let's look at at NUMA. NUMA is the
whole like how does memory attach GCPUs?
Uh because if you're running databases
particular stuff that needs to do a lot
of data shuffling, it's nice that the
memory is aligned with the CPU that the
process is running on. So how do you
kind of make that happen uh in a nice
way? Also from a scheduling perspective
like when you need to do feature
optimization, you also need to take that
into account. both the actual runtime
needs to the kind of schedule that we
have the ability to schedule but also
the like the actual scheduleuler needs
to be able to seem how do we best
allocate the CPUs to memory that's a
pretty hard thing to do and it's not
something you get around to doing
yourself but when you have a platform
like this you kind of get it for free
and I think the more of this stuff we
built the more people were like yeah
that's pretty nice
>> it sounds like this effort was uh kind
of a bottoms up kind of effort where you
and some engineers realize this is a
good idea and then it gained traction
gained traction. I'm curious like as the
the initiative evolved like did
leadership starting get involved at some
point and how'd that evolve?
>> We could really only get so far uh
because especially because uh back then
Uber like the stateful part of Uber was
basically split into two. One was like
the online real online uh databases uh
my SQL Postgress uh Cassandra stuff like
that and then there was all the data
stack uh ACFS Kafka Pino all that stuff
and that ran in a completely different
orc we had no like like the management
chain from that more or less went
through the CEO and back down so they
were like yeah this thing you're talking
about it sounds pretty nice but we
really don't care but but then at some
point there were there was some a game
going on but also
we got more and more support up the
management chain to like say this by now
this is something you have to do at some
point there was they just said okay this
Odin thing is the future and you will
not you will not be allowed to have your
own servers any longer you want to run
something that's where it runs um and
that of course helped a little bit also
with like uh adoption because you there
will always be like if you have like the
full button off thing there will al
always be straers or people who are just
like ah we don't want to or we have our
own thing going it's super hard to like
create like full alignments if you if
you're just yourself uh no matter how
nice the thing you have is there's
always going to be somebody out there
who's like ah
>> yeah I mean it's it's a huge undertaking
and I I feel like when you talk about
the end state of the entire company the
scale of databases all running through
this one platform that distinguished
scope makes a lot of sense. Um I'm
curious for for people who are wanting
to know about the career side of things
like how did that look at each step when
your career was growing through that?
>> I think in general
I think there many opinions opinions on
what how you get promoted what what what
triggers a promotion what I have like a
somewhat uh maybe naive hope naive
perspective on it that it's fairly fair.
is not always fair, but it's pretty fair
and it's tied to the scope of the work
that you're doing, the kind of the
amount of people you influence with what
you're doing. Uh that's kind of that's
how I see it. Um, and so like for
something like Odin that had like this
natural progression of first you're
basically doing it inside your teams,
then you're doing it inside your local
org, then you're going doing it inside
your um like the wider maybe platform or
and then it goes even beyond that. And
that that kind of reflects the the the
like the the job level also like the the
the more people you you have under your
influence not like it's not like a
direct influence but it's like the more
people who are like affected by what you
do well the the higher you get in the
level. Uh so if you're actually able to
kind of run a project of that scope to
success then I think a promotion will
happen or not not a promotion but a
number of promotions will happen
automatically and not just for you but
the like the entire team it kind of
drags a lot of people uh along. Uh, of
course you can say I was maybe a bit
lucky in the sense that I had a single
project for a very long time and a lot
of people kind of get shuffled around
and then do a project or the project get
cancelceled or fails and then you have
to do something else. Uh, it gets much
harder uh to kind of kind of write that
expansion. Not impossible. I've seen
many things where many is where where
where it's definitely possible but but
it's just it's much easier when like the
project you're working on has that
natural scope expansion. Uh so maybe my
promotions in to a very large degree
followed that work like first
first I did some background so I did
some other work before we got to to the
whole stateful thing and then I did uh
the the the first version of it. Uh, I
think that got me a promotion and I did
then then we did more and we kind of
expanded to to standard MySQL and
Cassandra and that that got me another
promotion to
I forget that because the title the
title names changed a bit on the way.
Um, but that probably got me to to
principal engineer and then when we kind
of only was more it wasn't done done but
it was like sets like it really didn't
require me any longer. was basically
handed off hand off to to the to the
team uh and I could do other things. Um
and that basically took me to the to the
distinguished uh engineer level. Um but
it was a very natural progression. It
was not a it was it was not a
progression I was like it was not that's
that was that was not the reason why we
were doing it. Uh it was just it
followed the work that we were doing um
quite nicely.
>> Right. I mean th those are the best
kinds of promotions. It sounds like
you're saying that the levels obviously
they're tied to your impact which is
tied to the scope of your influence. And
so I guess the natural question then is
what are the typical ways to have your
work being influencing more and more
engineers.
>> So I have this personal thing and that
is I just I just don't like doing things
too many times.
I just I really don't like it. Uh, and I
think I might have written something
about the the lazy engineer at some
point which like yeah I I like putting
these weird titles on things but the
idea that if I've done something like
for example I need to do if if I'm
operating a database and I need to
replace the host and I've done that
manually a couple of times I'm like I
this I don't want to do any longer. So I
that needs to be automated to some
degree or abracted away or whatever it
might be. Uh and so I think that's it's
not the only thing but I think for me
that is a major driver because then I'm
like why are we why do we have this
waste in our systems or in our
processes? Uh and I like when when you
start thinking about maybe not just your
own waste but also the waste of other
people. I think that's where you kind of
then you get into that scope expansion.
Uh so you kind of start thinking about
your own stuff then you team and you
kind of expand from there. So like that
that's that's how I think about it. I
don't think about it as like and it's
not like oh I need to like get promoted
or whatever. It's just I just have this
uh I just have this natural thing and it
can be pretty annoying sometimes because
you all you can kind of tend to rabbit
hole a little bit also or it's like a
what I what what we kind of call a depth
first approach to everything. uh where
like oh I'm doing this other thing but
suddenly this is annoying me I need to
build this tool oh but the tool is also
annoying to build so I have to build
this I have to build the build system or
I have to improve the build system but
the build system is also annoying so I
have to like whatever and then you take
it on a long chain of like [laughter]
completely sidetracking what you what
you should what you should be doing
that's kind of the danger of it but I to
me I I think it it just drives a lot of
of this like how do you actually improve
systematically and systemically like the
company and the processes and and in
particular your engineering
organization. Uh that's why I'm focused
but it can also touch other things but
mainly engineering. I I see the natural
leverage that comes from it because if
you build some tooling or something like
that that software can then act on your
behalf and help others and then that's
kind of how you scale yourself.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And and yeah. So like we
also talk about this whole thing about
like yeah how do you scale yourself? How
do you how do you come become a force
multiplier? Uh and it's something I
would like it's always like I don't know
then you can mentor people or you can
kind of whatever you can step we can
start like
doing more design so we can push that
down. I like the idea of like you become
a forceful supplier by allowing other
people to work better and faster or
maybe not even work at all ideally on
the thing that they're working on. like
take that problem away like think about
how do how do we actually take the
problem that you have like out of the
equation because I think that's the most
fundamental thing you can do like the
thing you were doing if you don't have
to do that any longer what could you
then be doing you one thing you
mentioned we're talking about promos is
you said they're typically fair and
they're based off of the impact of your
work but I'm curious it sounds like you
have some experience when promos are not
fair or what what does it mean when
you're saying promos are not fair
sometimes times.
>> Well, I think it can mean so it can mean
a lot of things and like I've been part
of promo committees for a very long
time. Um, and the promo committee
structure has also changed a lot uh from
like the first time I was in a promo
committee was I think the I wouldn't say
one of the scariest experiences of my
life. Uh but uh
but I
like so the first promo commission I was
in was basically uh for the entire
platform engineering. I forget how many
we were but it was like all the managers
and VPs and senior directors or whatever
and senior engineers in a room for an
entire day and then somebody asks okay
let's go says let's go through all the
candidates or wait let's actually go
through all our employees all our
engineers just all of them and then the
manager talks about like where how good
are they and should they get promoted
And then we just let it just and there
were like I don't know 200 or 5 500
engineers like I insane number and we
all and there was no preparation there
was no material there was just like the
manager saying what they thought and
obviously they all thought that
everybody should be promoted and then it
was like okay uh and then we should have
some kind of structure let's do some
kind of point system or whatever like I
is this how it works [laughter]
and and and it was back then apparently
and of course in in a setup like that it
gets super unfair because it all it all
depends on how good is your manager at
presenting your case and if you have a
[__] manager you have a [__] case
you might also have a very good manager
but your work is [__] so like so in that
sense there's a lot of unfairness going
on uh which I think also kind of led to
some of the early day Uber culture
issues not just just that but it was
kind of part of it um but anyway things
did get more structured Uh but it is
just super hard because it you cannot
there's just no way you can objectively
judge
how a person is doing because there's so
many dimensions. There's so many things
you're not operating in isolation. Maybe
you depend on like maybe the thing you
were doing actually depended on another
team and that team didn't do what they
said they would do. They just like
ghosted you or whatever. like
they didn't do it and it's like so what
that's not your fault or maybe you had
the project it was running it was almost
in production then it gets canceled by
management just for various reasons not
your fault but like then what like are
you then not getting promoted or are you
getting promoted and if if you're
getting promoted then on what basis like
is it just like oh because you wrote a
lot of code but the code was like never
used and nobody ever saw it again and so
like it's is hard because sometimes you
also like yeah you did a really good
effort and we don't want to demotivate
you completely by saying because it
didn't go to production it was not your
fault you're not getting a promotion. Uh
other times it's like you just also have
to make the thing where like you really
haven't proven anything yet.
You did a lot of good work but it's just
like was not your fault but you're not
getting promoted. Um, so yeah, ideally
there's just fairness all around, but I
think there's there is just inherently
in a in because it's a human process.
There's just a a fair amount of
unfairness. Um, and then I think there's
there's a lot of people who don't really
understand what it means. like they
think it's super unfair because they
think they did really well and compared
to maybe the team they did super well
but it's just also because the team is
not very well very good or you live you
lived on an island and you hadn't
realized that there's another world out
there that's actually very different and
more whatever um which I think just in
the early days of like Uber used to be a
Python shop well first like a JavaScript
Python shop. Then it went into a Go kind
of shop and like nobody knew Go. So
there was a lot of like a lot of people
just trying [__] out and so you would
kind of encounter these these kind of
groups of people who kind of had been in
under their own influence
and like and you just look at the what
they have produced and like this is not
this is no good. [laughter] Like this is
just no good. uh even though you you
kind of uh maybe yeah sure there's one
of you who's better than the other
whatever like but it's just like as a as
a whole it's just no good. Uh so we
cannot we just cannot promote you
because you need to look at what's going
on over here. Um and that can that can
just feel super super unfair to those
people. Uh because if they were not
prepared for what they actually went
into, I think that's also why I try I I
kind of made this effort of like trying
to describe how can you actually get
promoted like what does it mean? And
it's not about like I know like I I
think I call it something like beating
the promo committee or whatever uh which
can just like a a a catchy title but it
was really more about like what does it
actually mean to be a software engineer
at Uber?
uh because you have kind of all sort of
the ideas what that means but but
actually there is something there is a
way to be a software engineer at Uber
like there's there's and that way is
most likely different than meta or
Google or whatever and I think it's
pretty pretty important to be aware of
that because otherwise you kind of
worked towards something and that was
not the thing that it should have been
um and that that that can that can
create a lot of frustration and a lot of
disappointment uh yeah uh which uh and
it's and it's too bad uh that that
people can't get into that state and
don't get the correction uh along the
way that they go all the way to promo
have prepared a package written a lot of
stuff gotten feedback getting peer
feedbacks or whatever and then the the
promo committee is like nah it's no
good.
>> Yeah. you you said you wrote that piece
that was how to beat the promo committee
and it's basically you know the the way
that you grow as an engineer at Uber and
it's it's not focused on actually the
specifics of like the promo packets it's
actually focused on how do you become a
stronger engineer what was in there
>> mainly just to say like good engineering
practices and something that I found
surprising and like I actually found
surprising during all my years at Uber
which is well I don't it also met our
philosophy but I'm like a software
engineer needs to write code if you're
not writing code you're not a software
engineer I know that's some people find
that pretty controversial for some I
don't know why but like apparently it is
to me that and that applies to any level
like if your level if your title
includes engineer
you should be writing code and there's a
it might be different how much code you
write but you should be writing code on
a regular basis
um and to me regular basis means every
day. I know for some people might just
means once a week or whatever but like I
to me it's like every day uh ideally. So
like I think the main advice in that
thing was really just write code
don't don't mess around [laughter]
and and don't like don't overthink it
either like don't like oh I need to
write like advanced uh at my level code
or whatever like the the higher my level
the more advanced my code has to be like
don't no it just like just write code
because the more like if you have that
if you do that uh I have just never seen
anybody who will not grow along with
that and just keep writing the same code
like doesn't make any sense. Um so I
think that was the main advice was
actually just that just write code also
write good code like the secondary
advice and make make good good uh commit
messages and make sure to review code
and make your code nice to review and
all just like standard
software [snorts] practice which people
kind of I don't know forget a bit about
many people also like might not have
learned it because like normally you
don't actually learn like real life
software engineering out of college or
wherever you are, it's all theory. But
like in real life, there's just there
there's also there's also a
craftsmanship to it that you have to
learn and you don't learn learn that in
isolation. It's almost impossible to
learn it by yourself. Well, these days
you can get a lot of help uh from from
AI and whatever, but like you you have
to like see somebody doing it in order
to improve. Um, yeah. So, I think those
were really the that was really the main
thing and and there's a lot of other
things, smaller things about it because
you also need to be able to actually
articulate what you're doing like design
documents. You also need to like be out
there like you like having like my my
other one of my other philosophies is
like running code beats perfect code
anything.
I know you can always come up with like
weird S cases but in in the big picture
running code will always beat working
like perfect code or beautiful code or
whatever. Uh and that could be as as a
software engineer pretty hard to like
like some people because some people are
really oh no no like like it needs to
handle the cases and whatever. Um I I I
I I'm I'm just much more of like yeah
just do something because if you do the
perfect thing you get tied up in this oh
in order to kind of submit code I have
to have all the I have to do the entire
thing and it must handle all cases and
then you kind of work on some that's
where you kind of start working on
something and then you refactor and you
do some more and then event like after a
month you do a commit and
That's just not useful because you did
not get any feedback. You never saw it.
You might be on a completely wrong track
like god knows what.
>> One common advice I hear when people are
thinking about growing in their career
is that they have to scale themselves
and that often points them towards being
more and more of a delegator and more
and more of a tech lead. and they start
getting into this zone where they're in
these highle discussions in the design
docs but not actually writing any code.
What's your thought on that? Because
that's like a very common thing that
people will push on higher level
engineers say stop writing code go and
delegate.
>> Yeah. And like as like personally I like
I I don't subscribe to that idea at all.
I see that a lot. Uh this is also like
some it's also just about like to some
degree it's also what you about what you
find interesting and I I just like
writing code. I just do I have always
liked it. It's just like what I like to
do. I would probably like if I had if I
didn't have anything else to do what I
do but I would do if I didn't have a job
I would probably also do it. Uh so like
I just like it. Um, but I think there's
also just a very big overlap
between like just the between the
writing of code and the ability to like
um perform [clears throat]
uh at any level. Uh, and to me it's it's
like it's there are many facets to it.
Uh, I think one thing is if you're not
writing code, you lose touch with like
the system.
uh not on day one of course because like
on day one if you stop writing code on
day one and one month one it's fine
because you you kind of remember what
was going on but the system evolves all
the time and you forget how it is and
you kind of probably get a more more and
more high level like view of what's
actually going on inside the machine.
Um, so and that just means it gets
harder and harder for you to kind of um
design for the f future like the designs
you come up with will be more and more
uh decoupled from reality and be more
and more it might be idealistic. Uh
whereas like and then when it gets to
actually implementing it's handed off to
somebody else and they're like what is
this [__] Uh and who came up with this?
Oh, that's that that's that guy with the
with the whiteboard and like what and
and the documents like what who's that
to like say what we should should be
doing because we the actual problems we
have are like this. Um so I think that's
I think that's one main that's one major
thing. Um and tied to that is the is the
kind of how do you actually build a team
because as you say you need to scale
yourself that's for sure. Um or I think
another way of of saying you need to
scale yourself is you need to enable as
many people to work as efficiently as
possible. Um which I think is a bit
different than just scaling yourself.
It's getting the sounds that you're kind
of cloning yourself which is like
usually doesn't quite work. Uh
but if you need to kind of make your
team
the when I say your team like the people
around you the people you're supposed to
influence if you're kind of supposed to
kind of affect change whatever the
change might be it just is much easier
to do if they trust you. They know what
they know that you know that what their
pain points are and they that you that
they know that if you say something it
usually works out
or if they say something then you listen
to them.
Um and so that that decoupling kind of
it hurts in that sense because you get
new people in like of course the people
you work with before they will know you
so they're kind of okay but like people
start rotating in and out so you lose
more and more touch with both the people
and the system and that over time gets
you to it might be a pretty bad state
where yeah you're doing a lot of designs
and you're doing a lot of documents and
you're doing a lot of talking and
reviewing and whatnot but you lose more
and more touch with what is actually
going on and then um and this might be
just be an Uber thing uh but you get
more more hostility also and people
won't tell you to your face like but you
will be everybody will think who's that
[__] or who's that kind of guy to
like come and say whatever. So, you're
saying if if you're not hands-on, you
lose trust. And then people won't tell
you that you've lost trust. And then if
you try to influence them or or convince
them, they're going to, you know, not go
your way.
>> Yeah. I think I think at least I've seen
that a lot. Uh, and the the the the
other thing is if you're not like in
there, uh, then at least personally, um,
I I don't want anybody to tell me what
I'm supposed to do. Uh, [laughter]
it's not it's not that I'm not open for
input. Really like to talk about it, but
if you don't have skin in the game, I I
think you should stay out of my things.
Uh and then I will also promise to stay
out of new things. Uh uh if you ask for
help, more than willing to help. If I
ask for help, I hope that somebody will
help. But and so so that whole thing
about like if you kind of do this top
down, oh by the way, now we're supposed
to do this. People don't really know
you, don't know where you're coming
from, don't know why why you're saying
what you're saying. That just it just
creates a lot of mistrust and and in and
in some cases just plain hostility. Um
and and I maybe in the worst case people
will kind of say, "Yeah, that's a pretty
good idea." And then they will just
completely gaslight you and just like go
go back and not not do any of the stuff
that you talked about. Uh
probably the most annoying outcome that
you can get. Uh you said something in my
research, you said something somewhere.
said if a VP says the exact same thing
an engineer does, engineers will still
not fully trust the VP. And so yeah,
that my question is why don't engineers
trust management? Yeah, but I think it's
back to that um that if you don't really
like if you have somebody who you feel
don't really know what they're talking
about to some degree. Uh like they might
have an idea but they don't really like
and that but that idea might be
completely off because they haven't
really spent the time to kind of
understand what is actually going on.
Um, it might be that they're completely
right,
but but it's just it's just I don't
know. I don't know if it's just human
whatever nature or if it's just like if
it's just me. Uh, but [laughter]
but I I just I just know from myself and
from other people I've seen is like
somebody says something and if you don't
like if you don't have a connection to
them,
then it's just hard to like take at face
value. And if face value is all that is
or or force like authority uh like if
authority is the only thing
it just at least in
so this might also be a super local
thing here like in like a Danish thing
like because it's like there's basically
no structure anywhere. Uh but it's also
a thing in Bay Area where like authority
in itself
doesn't really get you all the way. Uh
it it and again people might like say
yeah not a smile and yeah that's that's
nice but if they don't truly believe it
and I have I have just seen so many
times where people yeah that's nice and
they just they they don't mean it.
[laughter]
And if you don't mean it, then how are
you supposed to successfully implement a
project? It would just it will always be
maybe it gets done, but it will be a bit
like it won't like if you if people
don't think it's a good idea, they don't
take ownership. It's just not going to
be really nice. Uh so and so I think
that just takes effort and it takes much
more effort than you normally like that
than you would like it to be. Yeah.
>> You had to influence a ton of people in
getting your project to scale across
Uber. So if Yeah. How do you influence
other engineers then and avoid that
situation you're talking about?
>> Yeah. And again like as I said before
like there's probably always going to be
be somebody somewhere who's like they're
never going to be convinced. Just never
go for 100%. Like that's one thing at
least. Um but but but to me it's really
like I I just believe a lot in leading
by example. like if you say this is what
you're going this is what we're going to
build then you help building and you
also take a lot of the pain and I think
in particular and there's also the thing
about like another thing that that can
very quickly happen is that the the the
the higher level you get uh the more you
can concentrate on the like the hard
stuff the stuff that you there that is
only you who can do um but but That's
really not a lot that only you can do.
Uh there might be a couple of things but
it's really not a lot. So all the other
stuff there there's some tendencies for
people to like say oh because I came up
with the idea I should also implement
the most interesting stuff or what are
new algorithms or whatever or like I
should play with the fun stuff. Um, and
sometimes you do that, but but I think
most of the time you should really
delegate that down. Like you should
delegate the hard stuff down, not and
just keep the easy not the easy stuff,
but um but the stuff that is kind of
boring and you should just do that
yourself because again, you don't have
to prove anything any longer. Once you
once you have reached a certain level,
you don't have to prove anything. You
can do what you want. And so at that
point it's much better to in in my view
at least push down the hard stuff to the
people who can like barely manage it and
then help them uh make sure that they do
that kind they're kind of in the right
direction and then let them kind of work
with that rather that take that yourself
and then delegate all the [__] work
that's that that doesn't help anybody.
Um and we have like we had like this
expression of like shoveling [__] It's
not a nice expression but it is what it
is. Uh there sometimes there's just like
in order to do something there's just
some some really [__] work in there. Uh
and if you take that work uh and like
the the other people do the do the the
fun work that will also it will give you
a lot of credit uh but it will also
allow them to grow much faster because
if they get challenged the rest of the
team they work much faster they they
grow much faster and that's just to to
everybody's benefit. Um so like that
whole thing that's also yeah the coding
leading by example and to me leading by
example just means writing code to a
very large degree. Uh and then taking
all this taking some of that stuff that
other people
that you don't really want to do might
also be improving documentation or
fixing weirdo bugs whatever it is. And
there's not a lot of like there doesn't
have to be a lot of like glory to it.
there's usually not a lot of glory to
it. Um, but I Yeah, I I'm a very strong
believer in in stuff like that.
>> Interesting. Yeah, that's the opposite
advice I I usually hear usually like as
you go up people say you got to do the
hardest parts, the most impressive ones
as well, complex ones to kind of warrant
it being worth your time and you push
out all the easy stuff to anyone that
can handle it that's not you. What's the
downsides of doing it that way? Yeah,
but it's also because it usually turns
out that the easy stuff has it's easy
because it's like it might be easy to
do, but then you're like, oh, this this
thing
why like why are we doing this?
And then you start thinking, oh, how can
we avoid doing that? So you kind of take
some of the easy stuff and it usually
turns it turns out to give that you can
kind of expand that to something that is
not trivial in any longer that actually
that actually did require you to come
in. It was not it was just the intention
or purpose. But when you come in and
look at like why are we why do we have
this many bucks like what is this? And
then you start thinking about is that
the because we have bad reviews because
we have bad testing because something
else and then you can kind of start like
how do we how do we kind of make that
better?
Um, so I think and I and I have I've
heard that the same advice a lot of
times and I had a lot of people come
before after promo committees or
mentoring or whatever saying oh how do I
how do I get the right project so that I
can get promoted or how do I like how do
I grow my scope or like and my advice
has always been the same
more or less forget about that part and
just start writing some code uh focus on
that just do something that works.
Doesn't have to be big. Doesn't have to
be anything. Focus on something that
works. And then every time you do
something, think about are we doing the
right thing here? Like are we
introducing because in a lot of cases
actually um when you build something you
actually introduce more work to other
people. You kind of build a system and
then you like oh this is nice for us but
then it actually turns out that for
other people now they have more work uh
because they have more systems to manage
or they need to configure some other
something else and have more stuff in
their head like how do you think about
how what what is the net overall result
of what you're doing and how can you
make that better?
uh and it just doesn't have to be big
things. Uh but if you like if you're
always working with that in mind, my
philosophy is that then the other thing
will come. Uh you don't have to like you
don't have to be like oh I I must find
something. Uh it will come. And I have
seen it not many times because there are
not many but I have seen a lot of times
where people like oh I need to do like I
need to be promoted and I need to find
the right scope. like just like relax
about that part and just focus on
providing value because once you do that
the other thing will come uh in most
cases again back to the fairness part
that cases where it doesn't come and
then too bad but like in most cases it
it does and I think it's to me it's the
by far the most successful way uh of
getting there. I'm curious as you
advance in your career because I think
this is a common thing some people
experience is did your role become more
political?
>> I'm always like what does political mean
exactly? Um
so I think there a couple things to it.
Um of course you have to talk to more
people so there's more talking and
there's more fighting because you have
to like promote your ideas. H well you
have to promote your ideas but not
probably worse you have to listen to
other people's ideas all the time uh and
because they also want something and
like I think maybe I maybe don't have I
have an opinion or you think that is not
that nice um so in that sense there's
there's a lot of like fighting going on
um I think you also get you get much
more exposed to
to like the realities
like when you're a junior engineer you
kind Oh, we're doing we're kind of doing
engineering and then somebody else has a
grand has a grand plan. They all know
what's going on. It's all under control.
Then you're like you realize at some
point [laughter]
nobody's in control. Like there's an
illusion of control,
but there's just like people randomly
getting ideas and pushing them out. Uh
and that that I think that part is
pretty scary. [laughter]
uh to to to like as a rational engineer
to get to the point where like okay so
we're making decisions just based on
nothing or because you had like a vision
while you were in the shower I don't
know
or like you talked to some other guy who
also don't know what they're talking
about and now that's the strategy um is
that politics maybe it is uh but you get
more and more like you get you get more
and more subject ed to that part and I
think that's that's pretty scary and
it's also definitely not for everybody.
Uh I didn't like it at all. I didn't
particularly like it. I can abstract
from it. I can just do my own thing. But
if you get sucked into that then it then
and a lot of people get sucked into that
because there's so much like oh we could
also do this and let's do a big plan for
whatever and then that takes like weeks
and weeks to do a plan and like
with inbox like okay now we did that
hooray. Um
and so and then there's the whole like
that that idea of like that thing about
like somebody somebody came up with an
idea and now that needs to get
implemented and there's a lot of push
back and all this stuff. Um and of
course everybody has ideas who gets
heard how do we get your how do you get
your idea in? So there's a lot of that.
Um,
my personal approach to all that was
really back to the whole thing about
like I don't need anybody to tell me how
I need to do my things. So I don't also
don't want to tell other people how how
to do their things. Uh and I also don't
like I I have never been like a like
career planner as such like I have not I
oh this is how like I get to this but I
also have a very strong aversion to
projects that I can just see are just
stupid or dead ends or whatever you call
them and just stay away from them and
let somebody else do that. And that's
might be a little bit unfair to those
other people sometimes. Uh but that's
kind of how how I kind of kept my sanity
was basically say, well, okay, this
thing I think you should like it's fine.
You're already enough people. Like you
have plenty of people. I don't need to
be involved. I I have I have my own
thing over here that I can do. I don't
need all that stuff. Uh and of course,
as long as my thing is significant
enough, because if you don't have
anything to do, you're kind of a little
bit then you need to engage with
something. But like as so as as long as
you have something going on yourself
that can kind of fill out your scope
then I like I just say no um a lot uh
and some people might also say too much.
Um, but that's kind of my way of staying
kind of staying a bit away from all that
because there is just there is a lot uh
of noise and I don't know
I just like to be blunt about it just
like plain stupidity in my view but like
I think some people probably call it
politics. I don't think I don't know.
Um, but I also have very low patience
for it uh for stuff like I think if
you're doing something let's talk about
it and do it. I don't want to talk about
we should do something and we talk about
that for hours or days or whatever and
then at the end of it we was like yeah
we could do it next year and like okay
that that was just a pure waste of time.
>> One thing that I hear some from some
friends is they want to avoid all that
stuff so they don't want to get promoted
because then the expectations get higher
of more of that other stuff. So I'm
curious, did is any part of you regret
getting promoted to such a high level
and having to deal with politics?
>> Well, there were okay there were times
when like this is like this just
if only. But I heard but again it really
also depends on how good you are at
resisting pressure
and just like being like being yourself
like resting in yourself. I know it's
like I don't know some kind of voodoo
stuff, but like how confident are you in
just yourself? And do you care how much
do you care about other people's
opinions? And if you care a lot, it's
it's hard. If you don't care too much,
uh it's it's okay. And I like and I I I
like because I had like the good thing
about by by the way, we were remote uh
office in Denmark, small office in
Denmark. And we worked a lot a lot with
the teams in in um in San Francisco.
And the good thing about that is that
our daytime was uninterrupted. So we
basically do whatever we wanted. The bad
thing is we didn't have meetings in the
evening. But it's like but you actually
had a day work like normal work. You
could just do whatever you want and then
you have meetings in the evening. And
that creates this nice like you you kind
of get fully sucked into it. you only
get kind of a couple of hours every day
get sucked into it which I think helps a
lot. Just having having the physical
distance and the time zone distance
actually helped a lot in that because
there was like a lot of other people
were like oh then you pass some BP on uh
in the hallway that oh could you please
come along and we just like talk about
something. Yeah. But we we couldn't do
that. Uh so I think that also helped a
lot.
>> We talked a little bit about influence
and just last question on this. I found
somewhere that you said the best outcome
is when the other person thinks the idea
is theirs. Can you elaborate on what you
mean by that?
>> Yeah. Um, and it's not it's not like it
doesn't happen very often, but I'm I'm
just always when it happens, I am is
those are the best days when I hear
somebody
talking to somebody else like when I
overhear a conversation maybe in the
office, somebody talking to somebody
else about an idea I had originally that
they didn't like.
Um, and then maybe a couple months later
or whatever, it's like they're saying it
and they're not saying that I said it.
they're saying it with conviction.
Um, and it can be it can just be small
stuff, but it can also be a bit lar some
some larger things like I don't like
let's let's just say like you have
resistance on like Odin where you need
to rebuild something because you already
had the tooling but now if you were
actually using you actually had the
benefits but you initially you were not
like able to kind of see through see see
through that and like go go kind of
beyond what you had yourself and see the
benefits of the other thing because you
were looking only at the cost. But after
a while you might have realized that
this actually a good thing. Um without
having been like forced into that you
just like a seed was planted uh and then
that kind of grew into something and
then suddenly that person is actually
aligned and you didn't do a lot. Maybe
you notched a couple of times or there
was like a team kind of not a conscious
team effort but like you get into an
environment and it kind of changes you a
little bit. Um, and like it's just a
couple I' I've seen it not many many
times, but I've seen it a couple times.
It's just like it's just the best
feeling. And it's not the best feeling
of like, oh, you were right kind of
thing. It's just um to some degree a
proud feeling of like those guys, they
learned they they're on the right track
now. And it was without force. Like
there was no force involved. It was not
just because you kind of forced it into
them. You we just need to do this. They
were like actually actually like oh yeah
this actually good idea that's truth.
>> I saw somewhere that you had some
unconventional advice for picking
mentees or just something that I hadn't
heard before where you pick mentees
specifically outside of your org and you
try to disperse them to increase your
influence. I'm curious to hear more
about how do you pick mentees?
>> Yeah. So men like Okay. So mentoring in
general is like it's a very like um
I don't know it sounds so nice and
appealing but it's also when you look at
like the whole thing about scaling
yourself it's like super inefficient
like because
you kind of paralyze it. You're like
you're you're one person you're talking
to one other person. Uh and there's only
so much time in you only have so much
time. Um, so like the it's just super
hard to get high value out of that. Uh,
so to me it was it was really always
mainly just about having a network
uh and having conversations that are
like two-way conversations. It's not
just me providing whatever. It's just
also them talking about something. And
that's where like if you go if you're
all mentoring inside your own like team
or or is like like who's who's actually
learning what now? uh and like the the
that close range mentoring I think you
can that is much easier to do at like
not at scale but you can kind of talk to
people in a group setting more easily
about like career advice or whatever you
can do a bit of like
informal like oh what about that and
what about but it doesn't have to be
like scheduled or structured in that
sense where if you go to people you
don't really know or they're further
away from you there's more work in it
and you also have to like there's also
more benefit for you because you could
learn something about what they're doing
you can give them more input on what
they could be doing or why they're doing
what and so like so that's I think it's
nice it's nice if you actually have to
like spend the time to to actually do it
so that you also get some kind of
benefits but also so that you can kind
of plant plant seeds elsewhere
um because I've also seen
a number of times actually that people
come in and say, "Oh, I just how do I
get promoted? I'm I'm I only get [__]
projects and like whatever." Um, but
then you kind of once they start
thinking about, oh, maybe there's
another way of thinking about the whole
thing, another way of working that will
kind of rub off inside their teams. Uh
so you're kind of planting a small seed
there that again will take a while but
might actually do positive change not
only to the mentee but also the rest of
the team and eventually the rest of the
orc. Um so that's why like
I I I prefer to like have people who are
not super close.
>> Do you have advice for mentees on how to
signal their potential to mentors? So I
imagine at some point you had probably
more asks for people to you know be
mentored by you or spend time with you
than you had time for. Um but let's say
someone's you really promising and they
really want to mentor from some person.
What would be your advice? How can they
you know set that up in a very natural
way? But I would I would probably start
like not just by asking oh can you do
mentoring because also because mentoring
can be kind of a mental load kind well
not a mental load because that's
something else but like it could be kind
of it could be kind of it can feel like
a big thing and a responsibility that
you might not actually want. Um, so it
might more be like, "Oh, can you help
with can you do can you help with
something specific or can we just talk
about like
something a design or a product we're
building or whatever?" Like just have a
conversation and then you take it from
there. I think that's that's one thing
you can do. Um, if if it's about like
how do you actually approach in the
first place, of course, always like cold
call and it works most of the time. Um,
I I usually didn't have that many
people. um reach out but there were a
couple of times but but um
but then also like just show up ask
questions like if you I had a lot of
presentations like in different offices
um and I always like when people like
come up and talk and ask uh so if you
kind of ask good questions uh I don't
know what question good quick good
questions are but like if you ask if you
just come up and ask and signal like
that I think that's that is a good
signal of interest. Uh and then just
because I I think it's also on the on
the mentor to kind of say, well, okay,
what you what you come and say is is
really not what you should be saying.
And I I don't think that should
disqualify because that's the whole
point. They need mentor. They need
mentoring. They might not actually know
what to say. Um, so, so I I I don't
think that if you if you want to do
mentoring, don't don't disqualify just
because they don't didn't send the right
resume or whatever. Um,
but they do have to have some
willingness to learn. And I think you
get you can kind of gr you can kind of
gauge that from just a like a short
discussion of like what are they doing,
what are the outlooks, what they have to
be doing, what are they thinking and see
how they do, how do they react to your
thing. Um and that might take a while
take just a bit of time like 10 15
minutes. Um and that's I think the other
thing is like to me mentoring is much
better if it's just pretty informal.
Like I I have like Uber has had have
been through different like a number of
different like mentoring systems or
platforms or [snorts] projects or
programs or whatever. And I'm like I
don't want a plan uh and I don't want a
schedule. that don't want anything
because like it's all individual what
people want or need. Uh so so also don't
just don't make it more than has to be
and also don't don't be afraid to say
okay I don't think we like kind of we're
done like or like I don't think we're
getting going to like you're not going
to going to get more out of it I'm not
going to get more of it. So this like
yeah it was nice
>> coming to the end of your career story.
I know eventually you left Uber and I'm
curious what's the story behind you
leaving Uber.
>> It's not a nice story unfortunately. Uh
I like I don't think so it is because I
was actually pretty happy on Uber. Uh
and um surprisingly so uh because when I
joined Uber I was like this like a crazy
like a crazy high pace place. When I
joined in 14,
it was also a very hot place to be and
people were coming from Google, Netflix,
Amazon like it like Uber was kind of the
place people were going to. Uh and then
you get a bit of like imposter syndrome
because like I didn't come from like big
tech is going I came from small tech. Um
so so I like all these people kind of
are much better than me. So like what
can I do? Uh and like I was talking so I
better like
I kind of hit the ground running uh uh
and never stop and that that that's can
also that that you can only do that for
so long. I'm like okay like I saw when I
joined and again I didn't have a plan
but like I wouldn't be surprised if I'm
out of there after like three or four
years because it's like it's like a
pretty intense environment. Um but it
turns out it was yeah it was intense.
also turned out that all those people
who came from the other places
well I don't want to like they were not
that much better than me after all
[laughter] uh it turned out they were
they were also just human um
and maybe more importantly they change
jobs much more frequently which means
it's really hard to keep a long project
running uh and kind of get the long-term
benefit of that but but even with the
high pace environment and the
performance uh performance management
and the
promos and all that stuff that is like
not natural to a like a Danish work
environment. Uh it was also just a whole
lot of fun. Uh and we had an office
with a very outsized
um um uh influence.
Uh we had a lot of senior engineers
uh compared to like we were a small
office but like we had very senior
engineers more or less from the get-go
and we just kept on getting more because
and we grew most of them internally a
lot of people grew to high levels. Um so
like in our office we grew two distin
distinct Indians which is like out of at
that point like 70 people it's like out
of 4 and a half thousand years that's
that's pretty insane. Um, so it was a
lot of fun and and we had these very in
like these these projects that we're
working on were very like challenging
and satisfying to work on and it was all
the stuff that if you're just like in a
normal company somewhere you go to
conference or whatever or you read about
blog posts and you reading about these
people who get to like do these
optimizations automations like ah if
only if only we had that like if only we
could do that and but we had that um so
like a lot of good stuff. Unfortunately,
it just happened that management
changed. Um, and that just
created this
uh change in engineering culture that
just meant that more and more people did
not like it. Uh uh and my managers
decided to leave at some point. He was
like my local manager who was also the
site lead. He decided to leave. Then the
the first distinguishing engineer in our
office decided to leave at around the
same point. Other people started to
leave. A lot of people left in the US
also and that just meant that it got
less and less fun and there was more and
more top top down kind of management
going on because initially in the old
days it was very engineering
oriented especially in platform
engineering where where I was. Uh so
very much uh very much not necessarily
only driven by engineers but engineers
were kind of part of the process when
you're designing something you were you
were there uh you were not always like
it was not always the thing you wanted
to do that actually was decided to do
but at least you were there you
understood the reasoning you kind of
stand behind it no almost no matter what
but it turn it kind of went to a place
where it was just like oh now we now we
need to do this and you're like that
seems stupid. Um and like there was this
decision of going to cl to to cloud.
Google had on-prem uh was operating
onrem had benefits and had downsides. Uh
and there was a decision that we should
move to cloud. Uh and the decision was
based on price that it was going to be
cheaper to run on cloud and no engineer
believed that also turned out not to be
true. It only turned out to be true
because then we had to cut cost of
platform by almost 50%. Then
it was cheaper but we we could also have
done that on prim and have have it like
then we just have even cheaper but so
that whole like top down management uh
just led to a full-on drain of uh
especially senior engineers because they
nobody really want to be part of it any
longer.
Nobody wants to be left out any longer
to some degree also. Um so at some point
I was also like I could stay but staying
would basically mean
that I would have to like um work in an
environment where a lot of a lot I
wouldn't be able to kind of uh stand
behind the decisions that were made. And
as a as a senior engineer,
if you're not behind the decisions that
are made, it's really hard.
Uh then you can just choose
my one of my peers or one of the
managers managers actually said when I
was like, I'm I think I'm going to
leave. He was like, yeah, but don't why
not just stick around and you just do
your own thing and just take the money
more or less. I'm like, yeah, sure. the
money the money is pretty nice but I
just I don't think I can do it. I don't
think I can witness
what other people are going through and
just like do my own thing. I just don't
think I can do it. Uh so at that point I
was like I then I was like then I have
to leave because I have tried enough to
change uh how things are done no effect
and that just means in my view that Uber
does not have the need for interviewers
at that level. as simple as that. Um,
and then I was like, then didn't then
yeah, at that point I had to leave. Uh,
but so to me it's a pretty sad thing
because it's like a self-inflicted thing
that Uber did uh for no for no good
reason in my view, but it just lost so
many really really good people. Mostly
two data bricks by now by the way, but
whatever. [laughter]
There's like a parallel world going on
there.
what made you want to go to a startup
instead of maybe data bricks or like a
big company again?
>> Yeah, so I think there are two parts to
it. Uh so data bricks pretty pretty nice
because they had also a local office of
open the local office. A lot of people
moved there a lot of people are new but
also just to build this to to build more
infrastructure and more or less to build
the same thing we have built once in a
while and I like we already built it. It
wasn't that [__] Uh, so like I don't
know if I want to do it again. Like
yeah, it was a lot of fun, but like I
don't know, maybe it's like like if I'm
if I'm moving somewhere, there should be
some kind of change. And it's nice to
have it like a an like a like what's
called a like a cultural change. It's
nice, but it would also just be nice to
like do something else. Uh, the other
thing is uh as as it's nice to be a
senior engineer, but it's also scary.
Scary when you change jobs.
uh because suddenly you get into an
environment where you don't know
anybody. They don't know you. You have
no reputation. Well, you have some
reputation from the outside but you have
no personal reputation. Uh and what I
have seen a lot of times is like people
come in super like senior years come in
they have like and they come in to fix
something usually they're like oh they
fix this thing over here they will come
in and they will fix it for us also. And
it's just never that simple. It's just
never that simple. There's almost no
chance that you can take whatever you
did over there and apply again with
success. Just it just doesn't happen. Uh
so and those people are just in for a
very rough ride because they will face
resistance from everybody. Not everybody
but they face a lot of resistance.
Everybody say yeah what told you
[laughter]
and will more or less cheer when they
when they fail. It's like I don't know
it's not super attractive to be a senior
engineer like that because like the
expectations when you when you come in
are so high. Um like some companies do
quite well because you kind of just they
say well we could like start slow and
you embed you into the team or whatever
not you're not from on day one kind of
but still there's just a lot of like
catching up to do and you have to like
prove yourself. Um, so it's not that
it's cannot be done and I'm not saying
that I I didn't want to do it at all,
but like I just didn't want to do this
like a natural move to another company
where to just do the same. I just like I
was like if you're doing something, we
might as well doing do something real
like drastic and the drastic thing is
just like the the complete opposite of 4
and a half thousand years is like
two million years or whatever it is. Um,
yeah. Yeah. So that that was basically
my my reasoning around it. It's just
like okay but like let's just and we can
because the other thing we can always do
the other thing always like can always
just go to data bricks or one of the
other places. I can even go back to Uber
if I wanted to. I don't want to but like
there's always there always the other
options. H so doing the startup thing is
like if you're doing it then yeah why
not why not just go all in on that. So
that was my kind of thinking around it.
Right. And since you've joined the
startup, how how has it been compared to
your expectations?
>> It has been very interesting. I would
say it has been a lot of fun. Like we do
we have like an AI enterprise automation
startup going. It's super interesting
and we we build so much stuff
um every day. Uh and we're kind of
navigating a space that nobody has ever
been in before. So it's like and so you
have to really be on on the edge always
which is like and I like it and I like
and I like also being and we're building
a product. We're not just building
infrastructure. I love building
infrastructure but it also gets you very
disconnected from like the reality. Uh
where here we're like building the
entire thing and I just like that a lot.
I don't like a lot the ah the
fundraising and oh we're about to run
out of money and then what and like that
whole thing. it can be a bit stressful.
Uh [laughter]
uh and yeah, so it's it's been good. Uh
uh it's been harder than I thought it
would be. Uh for for now, I would say
still still worth it. Uh not in not in
money. Yes, I hope it will eventually.
>> Coming to the end of the conversation, I
wanted to ask you some career
reflection. So, is there an engineering
mistake or the the biggest engineering
mistake that you saw happen at Uber that
was only obvious in hindsight?
>> I think it's hard because there were a
lot of choices that did not scale,
but at the point where they were made,
it was kind of the right choice. It's
just it got so painful later. Uh, does
that mean that you'd have done it
differently? I don't necessarily think
so. Um like for example I said like at
some point we were operating like 50
different databases or whatever. Was
that wrong as such? Well maybe that
maybe somehat that was wrong but but it
came out of the idea of like let
builders build like just like if you
need to do something go nuts. Let not
let nobody block you. Which once you're
10 years into it is an insane strategy
that's going to like kill you. Uh but in
the early days like you don't want a lot
of structure. You just because you don't
know what you're doing. You don't know
if you're going to be successful. You
have no idea what's going to happen. So
they go nuts. Um I think the hard part
is like when do you like when do you
expand? When do you contract? like how
how do how do you kind of manage that in
a good way and that's super hard uh and
I think I think some of the things is
that I think Uber really should have and
I don't really I have not really
reflected much on how how we should have
done it but that's definitely something
where like we should have better at
doing those transition from like full
freedom to more structure
um like one of our prime examples is uh
at some point we start doing tracing uh
back when Jerger was uh was built uh for
for distributed tracing pretty nice and
everybody thought this is pretty nice uh
and then there was like a mandate to say
okay we need to we need to enable
tracing all on all all our service
because we have a microser we have like
a thousands of microservices nobody
knows what's going on let's do tracing
because that will give us a lot of
benefit and then there was an email
going out
and I don't remember the exact dates I'm
guessing the first email was in 15
saying oh okay we're doing tracing. All
teams must implement tracing.
And there probably was a deadline 3
months later. And then 3 months later,
it's like the same because it had not
happened surprisingly. And then it there
was just like maybe until maybe 17, 18,
they was like, "Okay, this now we're
doing it. Now we're doing it." And but
it never got done. And somehow the
emails just stopped coming, but it never
got done. Like for real.
So [snorts]
that's inability to kind of affect like
global change
just made so many projects so hard. Um
and it's really to a very large degree a
cultural problem. But I think it's not
just an engineering problem but it's an
engineering culture problem. And I think
that I think to me that is probably the
one of the biggest things that
that to some degree hurt the company
because there was there's a lot of waste
a lot of waste going on. um that was not
necessary later on was necessary in the
beginning but they don't not um so I
don't think I don't have like a concrete
like oh then we did this and then it was
kind of stupid and we should have done
that where where it was like super
obvious well okay I'll just mention one
thing and that is uh at some point and
maybe somebody's going to be super angry
about this I don't know but uh at some
point we tried to implement uh a a kind
of software networking stack. Um and the
the team building it was like, "Yeah, so
we're going to do this uh thing where
you like we're going to build a software
network uh uh where like if you are when
when when services need to communicate,
it goes into an ingress uh and then it
gets routed through a network and to a
to to to the right service." And that
whole thing we implement in node
and I like I just distinctly remember
there was like a platform tech talk or
about like this is like insane but it
was back in 16 or whatever and I was
like not that senior yet. So I okay but
those people are pretty senior they must
know what they're talking about. turned
out they did not know what they were
talking about and that that caused a lot
of pain [laughter]
and many years of untangling uh and
whatever. Um so I think that that was a
pretty bad decision.
Sorry to anybody who who don't think
there was but I think it was
>> about Uber's culture. Um earlier you
mentioned that especially with the promo
committees that there's a bit of a
unusual culture of you know everyone
needs to sell their managers just
present their reports and you just sell
it in a big group and you alluded to
that at that time there was also some
other cultural backlash and I vaguely
remember that too like around maybe it
was 2017 or something like that where
there was a lot of stuff going on at at
Uber. What was it like for you
experiencing that at the time?
>> There's a fairly big cultural difference
between Denmark and Silicon Valley. It's
very interesting like and in many ways
quite entertaining. Um
uh so like so it was a bit weird to
experience because like many of those
problems we just was we just were like
are these like is this how people
behave? I thought we were just like
coding and having fun. [laughter]
Like what are you doing over there? Like
you're apparently doing something very
different. Uh so it was like it was very
well first of all quite disconnected
because like we were not like we were
quite far from that whole thing. Um or
maybe it's just me. I was like maybe I
was just very naive. I don't know. Um
but first of all it was it was good to
be at a distance because we like there
was a lot of stuff going on. We could
just keep on like executing and doing
our thing. So in that sense it was nice
but it was also it was also insane like
so that much stuff that was happening
and people leaving getting fired, board
members getting kicked out, Travis
getting kicked out. A lot of stuff going
on was like every day you like what's
going to happen now?
Um but again daytime quiet here because
9 9 hours time difference we can just do
our thing and then whatever happens
happens and there's not really anything
we can do about it. It's not like not
our fault. Uh there's some of it that of
course we also have to adapt to. Um but
there was very much like when I joined
there was very much like every
everything was very much about you like
performance reviews you promo you
conversation you like when you get hired
or and you negotiate your salary it's
just about how good you are at
negotiating. So it's all about you. It's
not about the team. The team doesn't
matter at all. It doesn't play into
anything more or less. uh which is
insane to me [laughter] like I don't get
it. So even though that was kind of how
how Uber works, we had never like gone
fully into that mindset. Uh so for for
us there wasn't that big of a of a
difference. Um it was more like okay now
like because I always thought like I
just thought that was how it was in the
US. Uh, so I was like, "Okay, so Oh,
it's not actually like you actually
wanted to be different." Like I thought
I thought you liked it like that,
[laughter] but but you don't I don't I
don't know why why you did it like that
then. But anyway, but it was very
interesting times and there was just a
lot of scandals also where we were like
why why did you do that? like why did
you decide to go to a strip bar or like
why did you decide to to kind of uh open
up somebody's private data and see where
they went? Like what what motivated you
to do that? I don't know. [laughter]
But like [snorts] what motivates a board
member to like on a live stream to the
entire company after a sec sexual
harassment scandal to say something
like, "Yeah, it's going to be nice to
get the women on the board because they
talk more." [laughter]
>> Oh, no. No. What's
>> that's so bad? Like what? Like what are
you thinking about? Like what is this
insanity? I have mixed feelings about
it. It was just I was just happy to be
at a distance and but sometimes you
could also just feel like okay bring out
the popcorn and like see what's
happening here because like it was just
it was very interesting times when I
went to the US to visit before 17. You
go to some of the offices people like
fist bump and then do you want a
whiskey? I don't know. It's like Tuesday
at 2:00 p.m. I don't know. Do I want
whiskey? I don't think so. Like I I
[laughter] don't know. Is that a thing?
>> If you look back on your career so far
and you knowing everything you know now,
if if you were to give yourself advice
when you just started in your career,
what would you say? Just try stuff and
don't don't be afraid just because it
looks hard or because those other people
look much better than you because they
might be better than you. Sure, but but
you can also get there. It's not it's
not it's not rocket science. Uh it it is
just computers. Uh and if if you like
computers, uh you're pretty well off uh
if you just keep going with that. Um, so
I think that's probably the main thing
in my view. It's like just let let the
let your curiosity take you where
wherever and don't just don't assume
that what you're doing right now is the
best thing you can be doing
because there's probably something
that's even better out there or or or
will will be soon. And then
don't don't just discard that just
because you're kind of having fun kind
of having fun now or whatever. Um, of
course it might be hard to like tell
which what what is better than what you
have now. Like you also just have to
take a chance sometime.
>> Awesome. Well, yeah, thanks so much for
your time. I really uh appreciated it
for the guests. I'll I'll link to your
socials in the show notes. Is there
anything else though you want to, you
know, point people to? Maybe something
you're working on or anything like that?
>> I think my LinkedIn profile is probably
the the most relevant place because like
that's where all the stuff I write. Uh,
it goes.
>> Okay, cool. Well, thanks so much. I
really appreciate it.
>> Awesome.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to